hi everybody welcome back to the 15 hour
long epic unity for J online vigil for
Julian Assange I am so proud and
privileged to have here with me today
CIA torture whistleblower John Kiriakou
this is a man who has literally changed
the course of changed political
discourse and I had a humongous impact
on what we know about what our
governments have been engaged in in our
name and with our tax dollars John
welcome to the stream
thank you very much glad to be back
Susie it's amazing to have you here
thank you so much John John you have
obviously really unique perspective and
experience and I had someone ask me
earlier today if there was one of our
guests who could talk about US and UK
involvement in rendition program
specifically and how this relates to
Julian's situation had he not sought
asylum and Ecuadorian Embassy or if he
is handed over in both cases what what
are the kinds of threats that he faces
it's a good question
there are different kinds of renditions
first there's just regular normal
renditions and that is let's say I'm in
Pakistan and I catch you and you're
Canadian I send you back to Canada
that's a rendition then there's
extraordinary rendition so we're in
Pakistan I catch you you're Canadian and
I send you to Morocco and I don't tell
anybody including the Canadian
government and god knows what they're
gonna do to you in Morocco and then the
Moroccans write a report with all of
your confession and they send it back to
me
that's extraordinary rendition of course
that's an excuse me that's illegal under
international law but it happens every
day it happens all the time in Julian's
case
I'm gonna get a little bit Bureau
bureaucratic here in Julian's case they
wouldn't have dared to to initiate an
extraordinary rendition because he's
Australian and because he's Australian
that protected him if he had been a
citizen of virtually any other country
in the world they would have and they
they could have and would have done it
because he's Australian that protected
him at least a little bit with that said
his only option was to was to go into
the Ecuadorian Embassy and it's because
the fix was in now everybody knows the
fix was in everybody knows that this was
not meant to be a fair process right he
was set up from the very beginning and
so the only alternative to to being
arrested by British authorities and then
immediately extradited to the United
States was to go into the embassy the
problem that we've all run into here is
that the u.s. government has literally
unlimited resources and they can wait
until the end of time and that's what
they've done while concurrently putting
pressure on the Ecuadorian government
the last time we did one of these
livestream suzi we talked about this and
the very next day on the front page of
The Wall Street Journal was an article
that was entitled Ecuador tells us it's
open for business and the entire article
was about how President Lennie Moreno
the new president of Ecuador was seeking
increased enhanced trade ties with the
United States that they wanted to at
least double the trade with the United
States well there's going to be a quid
pro quo and the quid pro quo is to throw
Julian out of that embassy I have no
proof of that
but I'm confident that that's the case
this is about money it's not about
righteousness or truth or Liberty or
anything like that it's about money
that's what Lenin Moreno has come down
to that's what
Fredo's now f marina had gone the other
way and here continue to protect Gillian
what types of not just threats but
actions do you think Ecuador would have
faced taken against its state and the
reason I'm asking this is because we
know about cross border incursions from
Colombia we know about the Ecuadorian
journalists who were assassinated on on
their border what do you think there's a
how fold the u.s. be prepared to go to
pressure a country like Ecuador who has
essentially thumbed its nose at the u.s.
over the course of the last six years
and sheltering Julian Assange I think
they're willing to go quite far actually
we've seen what they've done with other
countries you can begin with the
downgrading of relations which is not
uncommon you can you can reduce or
freeze trade and the goodness knows that
the US exports far more to Ecuador than
Ecuador exports to the United States and
then you can um you can begin a
harassment campaign you can encourage
for example Colombians to cross the
border you can encourage a a border
conflict with a neighboring country you
can encourage people to to reduce the
level of their diplomatic relations and
so over the long term there's there's a
cost to this I'm not saying that that
Moreno has nothing to lose by leaving
Julian in the embassy he does there's
there's a price to pay
I mean we all make decisions that have
consequences we all make decisions where
there's a price to pay
um he's looked at that price and he
appears to be deciding that it's too
high so there are a lot of little things
that the u.s. can do that might that
might result in in a you know diplomatic
difficulty for Ecuador but they can't do
anything that's terribly serious
and nor would they want to I think
because if you look at if you look at
the Julian situation and then you weigh
the entirety of us Ecuadorian relations
on the other hand the entirety of the
relations outweighs the Julian problem
and so I believe that I believe that
Moreno is is acting because of fear fear
of the unknown and that unknown is what
the United States might do if he doesn't
respond and if he lets Julian remain in
the embassy and I think that that
reaction really is an overreaction but
then on the other side of the coin
what does Moreno stand to lose by
cooperating with the US and by
potentially kicking Charlie now the
embassy by whatever means nothing he
stands to lose nothing in fact if you
look at it just in terms of raw numbers
he probably has a lot to gain his
relations will improve with the UK
they'll improve with the u.s. its major
trading partner I think he sees this as
as something that's not difficult to
decide what about the loss to the status
of Ecuador all right it's the thing that
to me and to you that's important
I wrote an op-ed yesterday for reader
supported news about ed Snowden and I
said that I would rather be I would
rather face another terrorist attack
than to give up my civil liberties
well if I were Lenin Moreno I would
rather keep Julian Indy in the embassy
and maintain maintain the world's
opinion of me as a freedom fighter and
someone who stands up for justice and
liberty than to just you know raise my
exports to the United States to me
that's an easy decision is there a
chance do you think that Moreno was
always intended to do what he's done and
that it was an act of infiltration that
he came into and became you know Korea's
number two and then I mean even Julian
and WikiLeaks were saying you know the
best option is if Moreno is it becomes
new president
etc etc dude am i like a conspiracy
theorist to think of that or do you
think that he just had some change of
heart once he was in power that's a
great question I don't think you're a
conspiracy theorist you know I think a
lot of us were fooled by by his first
name
Lenin right I think that we all thought
that here was a true left is progressive
this was a guy who's going to maintain
Ecuador's current policy and any fooled
us and you know I I think that
infiltration is a is a possibility I
doubt that he just changed his mind
overnight I think he had fought this out
and and decided that once he was in
office he was going to implement this
policy because it wouldn't be the first
example in human history of having a
second in charge play nicely until the
day comes at the end power and into a
180 that's right it happens all the time
I think we've we've seen that in u.s.
politics as well yes actually definitely
yes okay so moving on to Julian's
physical situation now in the embassy
yeah you talked a lot about the
isolation that whistleblowers face when
I last spoke with you
what is your take now because there's
this really terrible catch-22 where
Julian's health is degrading fast yes
and his doctors have acknowledged that
there is a mortal risks to him in his
current circumstances and yet there may
be an even bigger mortal risk to him
leaving the embassy I personally don't
believe that the UK is going to treat
him with kid gloves and wait yesterday
to the US I think they've waited eight
years to get their hands on him and I
think the CIA will be on the first plane
to London if Julian is in custody that's
my personal belief I don't think they'll
even wait till extradition they'll be
they will be interrogating him within
minutes as my personal belief is the way
out here
I mean if he's a visa motor risk in the
embassy and if that motor risk outside
the embassy where is the where's the
open window that that's difficult first
first let's look at Julien's time inside
the embassy this is solitary confinement
you can describe it any way you want
maybe he used to have some internet
access maybe the food's a little better
but this is solitary confinement it's
not only solitary confinement but it's
solitary without the benefit of the one
hour a day of exercise outside so of
course his health is going to degrade
that's in part what the US and UK
government's have wanted to happen
because they knew that they could weaken
him over time and there's really nothing
he can do about it I mean the guy the
guy never has direct sunlight he's he's
in danger of vitamin deficiencies and
and rickets and liver problems and
kidney problems and everything else that
comes with not being able to to have
sunlight to break down the vitamins for
your body also look at look at the
mental and emotional situation that
people in solitary confinement suffer
from it's not unusual it's actually
quite common for people in solitary to
simply lose their minds and we know this
because we have very very long-term
solitary confinement here in the United
States in fact the United Nations has
declared the u.s. practice of solitary
confinement in US prisons as a form of
torture and as a human rights violation
you know we've we've had people we've
had people in solitary confinement here
in the United States for as long as 44
years that's 44 years without human
contact 44 years without seeing the Sun
that is certainly cruel and unusual
punishment the United Nations guidelines
are that no one should remain in
solitary confinement in one stretch for
longer than two weeks
Julian's been in solitary for six years
so of course that's going to take a toll
on his physical and mental health
there's there's almost
thing that he can do to avert that let's
couple that with his treatment by the
British government before we even turned
to the US government the British
government has been absolutely steadfast
in their promise to harass and humiliate
him the moment he walks outside that
embassy they have spent millions of
pounds of the British taxpayers money
just to keep him inside that embassy
ringing it 24 hours a day why the only
crime that he's wanted on is failure to
appear which is something like a 50
pound fine well we all know that that's
nonsense we all know why the British
have that embassy ringed it's to snatch
him and to turn him over to the United
States I have to agree that if that
happens the CIA and the FBI are both
going to be on that plane and they're
both going to be excuse me they're both
going to be at least attempting to
interrogate him all the way back home
they will bring him back to the United
States in Chains because that's what
they do I said last time I did one of
these live streams that the rumor here
in Washington is that Julian has been
secretly indicted in the Eastern
District of Virginia that's here where I
live in it's based in Alexandria
Virginia and they call the Eastern
District of Virginia the espionage court
because almost all national security
cases are tried here and the reason
they're tried here is because this is
the home of the CIA of the Pentagon and
of almost every intelligence related
private contractor in the Washington
area so look who's going to be on the
jury it's gonna be CIA employees FBI
employees military employees or their
spouses intelligence contractors or
their spouses
Julian couldn't possibly get a fair
trial in a place like this so they do it
on purpose now besides that no one no
national security defendant has ever won
a case
in the Eastern District of Virginia it's
called venue shopping even though no
crime was actually physically committed
in the Eastern District of Virginia they
know that the judges here are the
toughest in America on national security
cases and so they would charge him here
you wouldn't charge him in New Mexico or
California because he would probably be
acquitted so they charge him here in the
Eastern District of Virginia so my hope
is something that's actually not even
legal
my hope is something called jury
nullification jury nullification is when
a jury hears a case the person violated
the law and the jury finds that the law
is unfair the law shouldn't be the law
but this is a miscarriage of justice and
so even though the government has been
able to prove its case the defendant is
found not guilty it's not guilty because
the law is wrong and it's unfair and
that's really my hope for Julian in the
event that the worst case scenario
actually comes to comes to pass and he's
extradited to the United States I hope
that there are 12 people or even one
person because in the United States
juries have to decide unanimously in
federal cases just one person to say
wait a minute this is wrong it's wrong
for this man to be prosecuted and so I'm
going to stand up and I'm gonna say no
now that'll that will result in a hung
jury and that's fine he'll probably then
be retried but you can retry him over
and over and over again and if one
courageous person says no then
eventually it's going to come to an end
and he'll win
so daniel ellsberg when I spoke to him
firmly believed that Julian would be
used to create case law to create a
legal precedent whereby a journalist had
finally been successfully prosecuted and
that that would then be used either as
the stick or the threat or to actually
continue to prosecute other journalists
Chris Hedges and I talked about hinges
being party to the action against the in
DAA which was the Obama and definite
detention Act which applied to American
citizens and he just talked about how
when they tested their in court the
government was able to be to it
essentially what it came down to is that
they were who just believes that there
are already American citizens who are
being indifferently attacked who are not
being given due process who are not am
able able to even be they're not even
given charges and tried in court they
just literally indefinitely detained the
same as has been done to so-called
foreign combatants prior to that and
certainly when we we also talked touched
on like the Chicago Police and black
site and these other black sites in the
United States where these arbitrary
arrests and detentions have been
occurring which is along the same lines
in the a so what I'm thinking is there's
two options one is that they do
prosecute Julian because they want to
create the prints that the precedent or
two is that they then there is a danger
that they might not prosecute them at
all that they might not even charge them
but that they'll indefinitely detain him
do do you think that it's possible I
think it's possible but not likely first
of all I think Chris Hedges is right and
I think Dan Ellsberg is right as well
Chris Hedges in that we know from the
ACLU that there is at least one American
citizen being held indefinitely right
now without being charged we don't even
know if he's being held in the United
States and we aren't entirely sure if he
is
American citizen or has dual nationality
there are rumors that he's a dual Saudi
US national and that he was scooped up
on the battlefield in Syria but you're
right the India the NDAA the National
Defense Authorization Act which Obama
pushed that allows for the indefinite
uncharged detention of American citizens
is enforced as law Americans no longer
have to be charged with a crime you can
be held for the rest of your life
incommunicado die in prison and no one
knows that you were ever there that's
not the American Way but that's what
we're doing so Chris Hedges is right
before I get to Dan house Berg let me
finish this thought Julian is so
high-profile and has so many supporters
and is Australian that I think that
that's just not possible
if the Australian government likes him
or not it's irrelevant they have to
protect the rights of their citizens
overseas and so whether the Australian
government likes Julian's politics or
not makes no difference they're going to
have to weigh in with the US government
on a consular level to make sure that
his rights are being protected so I
don't see any scenario where Julian
disappears into the system Australian is
likely to do that because I mean really
they have not seemed to get was a new
zone they don't seem to have given a
toss about Julian for the last however
many years it's only very recently that
they've actually you know had any
consular assistance provided to Julian
than the Ecuadorian Embassy and
certainly New Zealand and Australian
citizens both very much feel that our
governments a vassal state they are the
servants of US Empire so is really
realistically being an Australian
citizen going to make that much
difference I think it will in that it
will keep his profile high like I say if
he had been a citizen of Somalia or
Yemen or Algeria he would disappear and
no one would ever think about him again
but because he's so high-profile and
he's Australian the Australian
government is compelled to
least pretend that it yes to pretend
exactly
dan Ellsberg makes a very very important
point here he's exactly right that this
is a test case and I think that we got
an indication of that in the very
beginning when then CIA director Mike
Pompeo who's currently Secretary of
State said that WikiLeaks was a hostile
foreign intelligence service can you
imagine that I think of those words are
hostile for an intelligence service like
Iran or North Korea they said none says
it I said non-state hostile non-state
intelligence service non-state well al
Qaeda is a non-state actor
Isis is a non-state actor they collect
intelligence this is what he's comparing
WikiLeaks to well we all know WikiLeaks
is a journalistic organization everybody
knows that they're just pretending that
that's not the case and so they're going
to treat WikiLeaks
as though it's a hostile non-state actor
now in the event that a US jury again in
the Eastern District of Virginia most
likely decides that that's the case then
it's going to be open season on every
journalist think back to toward to the
days of the Obama administration those
were dark days for liberty personal
liberties and civil rights in that it
was the Obama administration that that
went through James Rosen's notes this is
a Fox News journalist and accused him of
being party to the leak of classified
information and then identified him as
an unindicted co-conspirator this is a
journalist doing his job is described as
an unindicted co-conspirator you don't
forget that it was the Obama
administration that ordered authorities
to raid the home of a Washington Times
journalist
to steal her notes from a locked cabinet
because they thought that she might have
uncovered some kind of wrongdoing in the
military so little by little the Obama
administration pushed that notion that
the press was hostile that the press was
too well protected by a legal precedent
and that they were going to start
dismantling that but they lost but they
lost each time the teesta in court
ultimately they had to back down they
lost so when you say Julian is a test
case what you mean is that this is their
chance to maybe not lose yes because
look they have nothing to lose by
charging Julian I mean if they lose the
case okay well they're back where they
started that doesn't mean that they've
that they've been pushed back in terms
of policy if they win they set a new
precedent and everybody's in danger so
when will the priests wake up to that
fact do you think it's starting to
happen there has been some rumors from
some journalists that seem to be
thinking Ryan grim DC bureau chief or
the inserts comments last week's last
week some of them seem to be having a
self-reflective moment and thinking
maybe this doesn't make such a great
idea for us to cheerlead this on however
I talked to Peter LaBelle earlier who
said he does not believe that we will
see the day that the New York Times and
Washington Post crowd championing
Julian's cause you know in order to
protect press freedom as a whole do you
think that will reach that worship
moment or or not well let's look at what
the US press did with Ed Snowden how
they treated ed Snowden the New York
Times eventually after a period of about
four years called for ed Snowden to be
pardoned on its editorial page
The Washington Post another newspaper of
record here in the United States called
for Snowden to be prosecuted for treason
that's a death penalty charge the Los
Angeles Times editorial board wrote
wrote editorial
taking both positions he should be
pardoned he should be charged and tried
and convicted so when the owners of
these newspapers the publishers and
editors of these newspapers either can't
come down on one side or the other or
come down on the wrong side I think that
we oughtta fear for Julian safety and
very much we saw that extended to what
you're describing extended to the UK
press as well as I remember this is even
worse to tell you the truth yeah I think
the UK press is worse because so much of
it is so conservative and then even the
Guardian I have to say I'm disappointed
in the Guardian
visa vie at Snowden because the Guardian
was was a recipient of Snowden's largest
as was the Washington Post and they both
turned on him I don't understand that at
all Joanne once by Skype at a Ron Paul
event a year or so ago really I must
have seen that I've seen Julia on Ron
Paul but I didn't recall you guys being
there together
it wasn't available in wrongful sorry
yeah it was an event at the Davos Expo
Center in Virginia I just happened to be
sitting in the front row and there
happened to be a camera pointed at me
and Julian said oh there's John Kiriakou
and I said hi Julian are you well
because I know he's a huge fan of your
work and I know I'm WikiLeaks as a whole
as a huge fan of your work and every
sacrifice there's I am if there's look
we would be without WikiLeaks we
wouldn't have any idea that the that the
US government was spying on American
citizens we wouldn't have any idea
thanks to Ed Snowden and WikiLeaks
we now know what NSA does and it's now
after five years that that the Congress
is finally starting to focus on these
different provisions in the Patriot Act
and in the face act as
as being anti-democratic and and as as
being anti Civil Liberties and it's only
because of Ed Snowden and WikiLeaks go
back farther and let's talk about
Chelsea Manning the complaint in the
press was that Chelsea Manning had
released so many State Department cables
and it it showed people's identities etc
etc it's irrelevant we know now that
there was no negative fallout from the
release of those cables what's important
is that Chelsea Manning released video
evidence of a war crime and we would
have no idea what for which there has
been no straight right like to this day
the people are involved in that are at
large they are they're free but elite at
least we know about it and that's
because of WikiLeaks
and so what we need is we need more
people passing information to WikiLeaks
look you know let's let's say the
definition of whistleblowing again
because I think this is so important
this is actually a legal definition here
in the United States whistleblowing is
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud abuse illegality or threats to the
public health or public safety okay
there's no downside to that there's no
downside to whistle blowing whistle
blowing is only a positive event for the
public and so we need more people
cooperating with WikiLeaks not fewer
do you think that WikiLeaks releases
have made anybody in inside the military
all the intelligence services I think
twice about their actions oh I do I do
when you when you shine light into the
darkness everybody reacts let's look at
this Chicago black site
the Chicago Police black site you know
when this when this reporting first
appeared in the US press most people
didn't believe it they thought it was
some kind of a hit job a hit piece on
the Chicago police because if there had
been a black site here inside the United
States people would have known about it
well nobody knew about it and we only
learned about it because of an intrepid
reporter who told us and so changes were
made people were prosecuted I can't help
but to think that because of WikiLeaks
people say to themselves maybe I ought
not to abuse this prisoner because what
happens if it leaks maybe I ought not to
participate in this whatever this
illegality is because it might be
released to the press
it might find its way to WikiLeaks so
that's only a good thing and I'll say
one other thing about WikiLeaks and I
say this all the time in in press
interviews people ask me if they have
information sensitive information
classified information government
information and they want it to get out
but they want to do it anonymously who
should they send it to and interviewers
always say well you know the New York
Times has a an encryption key on their
website and so does the post and so does
the intercept no no no you can't trust
those journalistic outlets to protect
your identity we already have seen what
the intercept has done with people's
identities over the years at least three
times the only place to go is WikiLeaks
WikiLeaks is the only organization
literally the only organization that has
consistently protected the identities of
its forces only WikiLeaks
um John I know that UK caged the
organisation UK cage and also big
friends of WikiLeaks and they they said
it was on their Twitter account they say
they're working to empower communities
affected by the war on terror and to
promote jus process they a number
amongst them Guantanamo X grant animo
prisoners and and people victims of
rendition I'm interested to know can you
cite any examples within WikiLeaks files
that have included revelations
specifically about rendition yeah there
have been a couple actually I've taken
calls from British journalists several
times asking me about renditions through
Diego Garcia and before WikiLeaks nobody
knew that there were renditions through
Diego Garcia and nobody knew and this is
even more important nobody knew that the
British were involved so that was a
great service I think that WikiLeaks
provided to the British people today
today has there been any come up come up
ins as a result of they rendition I mean
hesita been held accountable is there
saying any as I inhibited the programs
at all I mean I did some study into
rendition think a year or two back and I
discovered that there was something like
40 countries that had been involved in
it including like ends here and
Kazakhstan and like Brazil was one of
them actually yeah it's terrible isn't
it
[Music]
I've been out of the CIA for a long time
I left fourteen years ago now but it's
my understanding that yes this has had
an impact on the on the program
extraordinary rendition now is something
that's very very unusual and it's
because light has been shined on it it's
because the information has gotten out
and these countries don't want to be
held accountable so it's better for them
just to not participate in extraordinary
renditions anymore then to do it and
keep their fingers crossed and hope that
remain secret again anytime light is
shined on this darkness it's a good
thing because changes are made even if
those changes are incremental changes
are made you know we always say Susy
that governments always take the
long-term view they know that they're
going to be there forever they know that
they can outweigh most of their
opponents well you know what so can we
we can fight this thing forever we can
fight it year after year after year
because we know we're right and so if we
look at the long term like governments
do we're gonna win this thing in the end
a Nuremberg and you know even what we've
been pursuing noonah sorry Nazi regime
still works for into the 90s it would be
very nice to think that one day some of
these guys even in their 90's might
actually be held to account we've had a
long discussion on the stream with other
guests about how WikiLeaks is revealing
their crimes but these crimes appear to
be perpetrated with impunity from the
street level and like police every day
police violence to the nation's state
level and you know the subversions of
democracy we have voter fraud or you
know other revelations that have been
made about political fraud to the
international war arena where the UN has
twice ruled in Julian Assange's favor
the inter-american Court of Human Rights
has ruled and Julian's Julian Assange is
favored and the yet the US and the UK
just basically thumbing their nose at
international law and at those findings
how do we get from transparency to
accountability another good question
accountability I think is going to have
to come from individual judges you
remember when a woodstove Pinochet was
indicted in I think it was Spain
a decade or so ago it was because of one
courageous Spanish judge and one
courageous Spanish prosecutor we know
that the u.s. is going to thumb its nose
at
international law like it always has and
so will the UK they know they can get
away with it there's never any
consequence there's never any price to
pay so what we need is to encourage
individual prosecutors and judges now we
know that they're out there we know that
there for example there's a prosecutor
in Berlin who's considering charges
against Jena Haspel the the new CIA
director for crimes against humanity for
her role in the in the so-called war on
terror we need more people like that
it's it's no accident that George Tenet
the former CIA director has never made
an overseas trip since he left that
position he knows what he's doing he
knows there's a risk of being arrested
and charged with with horrible terrible
crimes if he leaves the country well
what we need to do is to make them
fearful we need to ensure that they're
fearful by encouraging these prosecutors
and judges to file charges final heavy
charges crimes against humanity war
crimes human rights offenses we need to
hold them accountable and the UN can't
so the individuals must interestingly
there's a Snowden cable that talks about
how in the war in Bosnia they military
chain of command made generals sign off
on bombing orders because they were
concerned about war crimes accusations
and so they they created the system
where at the topmost levels they had to
authorize everything because they knew
that there there were that would
indemnify those generals whereas if the
mid or lower rank people were the ones
signing off on it there was a very real
chance that they actually would be held
accountable and just backed the
renditions topic there was of course the
Italian affair which you could probably
tell us about where there was actually a
prosecution boy was there yeah before I
get to that let me
give you one little factoid when I
reached a certain level at the CIA in
terms of seniority I was offered several
different kinds of insurance so for two
dollars a year I bought it was called
dread disease insurance you know you you
work in these horrible places around the
world you're gonna catch something and I
did several times
well that dread disease insurance for
two dollars a year covered everything
that my regular health insurance didn't
I was also given legal insurance so for
another six dollars a year if I were
ever to be implicated in a war crime or
a crime against humanity the CIA would
pay all of my legal expenses now that
that was a relatively new development
that that's a post-911 development and
it's because they knew they were
involved in war crimes and crimes
against humanity and so at the very
least what they can do for their
employees is pay for their legal
expenses now the the milan affair this
this ought to be taught as a class at
the CIA on how not to conduct a
rendition operation there was a an
egyptian national in milan abu omar abu
omar was a firebrand muslim cleric who
would give the very tough anti-american
sermons after Friday prayers in the
mosque in milan well the CIA decided
that he was a threat and he was probably
al-qaeda he was probably a terrorist we
needed to shut him down and so they sent
a team of oh I think it was like a dozen
people to Milan and they surveilled him
for several weeks and they realized that
that he kept a schedule and he left his
apartment every single day at the same
time and he walked to the mosque so they
set up in a van on the route from his
apartment to the mosque and one day as
he was walking past the van they opened
the side door very quickly they snatched
him and
kidnapped him they bundled him onto a
plane and they flew him to Egypt in
Egypt he was tortured mercilessly right
and we know that because he was totally
innocent of anything and the Egyptians
finally came back to the US and said
listen this is either the wrong guy or
he's just innocent and they had to let
him go and now he gives interviews and
he'll show you the marks from his
torture well the Italians were outraged
by this because here's the US government
carrying out a criminal action on
Italian soil without anybody's
permission like we own the place
and so the Italians were compelled to
prosecute these dozen or so CIA officers
well almost all of them were operating
under pseudonym right not operating
under their real names except for Robert
lady who was the chief of base in Milan
Robert lady was charged with several
serious crimes he ended up fleeing and
he retired in Panama the Italians asked
the Panamanians to extradite him and
they briefly arrested him but then under
heavy pressure from the US they let him
go and then he moved to the US just for
his own safety now these other these
other CIA officers made mistakes every
one of them for example if you are
operating overseas under pseudonym
don't use your credit card that's in
your real name to buy souvenirs what's
wrong with you
are you stupid another one if you're
operating under pseudonym don't call
your wife at night to see how she's
doing what you need to do is buy a phone
card find an anonymous random telephone
booth and then call don't call from your
hotel and so the Italians very easily
were able to identify every single one
of these CIA officers and they indicted
them all well one of them is actually a
dual u.s. Portuguese citizen and she was
visiting her mother in Portugal and the
the Italian authorities asked the
Portuguese to arrest her which they did
and they held her for extradition her
case went up to the to the Supreme Court
of Portugal and the Supreme Court ruled
in favor of the government and so she
was extradited to Italy for trial now
these these are charges of kidnapping
we're talking 10 20 years in prison for
this well of course as soon as this
happened Barack Obama put ridiculous
pressure on the on the Italians and the
Italians pardoned her and released her
she was the only one that even came
close to facing justice everybody else
got away with it scot-free but probably
would be thinking twice next time it
would heart you have to you have to
think twice you know there are so many
examples Susie of the CIA grabbing the
wrong person look at look at Maher Arar
talk about somebody who was wronged this
is a professor at the University of
Toronto who was snatched from a plane at
John F Kennedy Airport in New York and
sent to Syria for torture he was
tortured for a year and a half and
finally the Syrians came back and said
this is the wrong guy and it was the
wrong guy that was suing the Canadian
government he got a six million dollar
settlement but the US as policy never
apologizes we
settle and we don't apologize I felt
compelled to apologize to the guy on
behalf of my own government because of
the way he was robbed and there are half
a dozen examples like that there is um a
article and opinion piece written I
think last week from my longtime
Guantanamo detainee I think he's been
there 14 15 16 years he was a taxi
driver in Karachi and they snatched him
and shipped him up to Afghanistan and
then on to Guantanamo Bay and and
tortured him hold him without trial as
the most gut-wrenching testimony
actually when you read through it he
talks about the types of torture that we
used on him and the total bleakness of
living in a situation where you can't
even receive a sentence there is no
light at the end of the tunnel you can't
defend yourself but you also can't even
have you know even if they gave him
twenty years at least you'd know in 20
years is getting out they don't even get
that no it's actually coined a term for
it at the CIA it's called learned
helplessness that that's the goal the
goal is to make you conclude that you're
utterly helpless and you just break
that's what they want to happen they
want to make you crazy so you're right
they snatch so many people a vast
majority of the people who've passed
through Guantanamo have been completely
innocent of any crime they were just
snatched right off the streets for
example if you and I are from the same
village in Afghanistan and I owe you
money and I don't want to pay you your
money back I go to the nearest American
and I say hey see that guy over there
he's al Qaeda they snatch you up they
give me a hundred and fifty dollars
reward they send you to Guantanamo
nobody ever sees you again and I don't
have to pay back that loan that happened
all the time sickening and I'm just
amazed I don't actually know how
humanity got to
go to a place where not only is this
happening but we know it's happening and
it's continuing to happen I mean how
long has gone have been opened now we
can't claim mag neurons right we don't
know you know I remember the first time
I ever heard about Guantanamo I was
serving in Pakistan and we had captured
Oh
dozens of al-qaeda fighters as they were
coming across the border from
Afghanistan after the bombing of Tora
Bora
and I remember loading him onto the
plane and I said to one of the Air Force
guys where are you taking them
and he said Guantanamo and I said the
basic want anima in Cuba and he said
yeah he said they came up with this
really great idea we set them we send
them to Guantanamo and we hold them
there for a couple of weeks until we can
get them processed in US courts around
the country and then we fly them to the
US to go on trial and I said oh that is
a great idea well then along the line
somebody decided now we're not going to
give them any rights we're not going to
put them on trial we're gonna make them
sit here for the rest of their lives
until they either commit suicide or just
give up and a lot of them commit suicide
and yet thirty US troops in Iraq and
elsewhere and there ought to be a lesson
for all what amazing what an amazing
outcomes that you have those four
prisoners and in some cases the guards
committing suicide how much our
governments have to answer for is
absolutely remarkable and getting back
to WikiLeaks then it's only because of
WikiLeaks that there is even a hint that
there could be justice because without
WikiLeaks we wouldn't even know most of
these stories absolutely
and if information is power then if
there is able to be any accountability
in the information that is the first tip
to that the awareness is the first tip
to that I didn't I haven't really had a
chance to speak with you about it I did
tell you a little bit on the phone but
one ray of light in my life at the
moment and hopefully in Julien's is
there over the course the last two weeks
this movement has become more than just
a series of vigil online vigil events
has become a daily coordinated action
group on a platform that we developed
there amazingly attracted 2600 volunteer
sign ups I'm in the first four days it's
been around for about ten days now and
is producing incredible content and now
moving towards on-the-ground actions do
you have hope there initiatives like
that where people can put aside their
politics turn away from the dividing
conquer agenda and collaborates a free
jewel in that maybe this you know if the
international law isn't going to work
and if diplomacy is non-existent can we
together make a difference absolutely
yes absolutely yes I'm very fortunate to
work with a guy named Brian Becker Brian
is one of the founders of an
organization that that does large scale
actions demonstrations sit-ins protests
it's called the answer coalition and his
work in the anti-war movement is its
positively inspirational Brian and I
talked about Julian all the time
along with dyani barreto and Randy
critic oh and other supporters of Julian
and Brian is confident that once we move
this into the streets we can have an
impact he's able to and I've actually
seen this with my own eyes
he's able to say I think I'm gonna file
a petition to close X Y Z Street in
Washington in two weeks for a March and
then somehow 50,000 people turn up how
he's able to organize that I have no
idea but I've seen it with my own eyes
and I know that if he can do it we can
do it
and certainly he would help us do it but
yeah I think we could have an
honest-to-god impact if we take to the
streets and you're right our government
isn't going to help us do anything and I
don't trust the media to help us do
anything we have to do it ourselves
sadly nor the NGOs during much about ADA
and they seem to react belatedly to
where there is existing large-scale
public pressure rather than helping to
create that large-scale public pressure
yeah where's the ACLU in all this and
why isn't the ACLU filing charges on
behalf of WikiLeaks and Julian or cases
rather I'm disappointed I have no answer
for that but I have noticed that the
statements from HRW and others seem to
turn up when there is ramping up in the
public discourse in support of Julian
and WikiLeaks which is really
disappointing because I would expect
those NGOs to lead the charge on these
issues and not just to be reactionary
well when I was arrested they ran
screaming from the room I got literally
no help from Amnesty International Human
Rights Watch or the ACLU nothing so if I
were Julian I wouldn't if I eventually
come to the party though what he wants
you had a high enough profile that it
becomes official to them to associate
themselves with the a eventually Human
Rights Watch did and then it was only
thanks to aiwei way that the that
Amnesty International finally came
around and it was because Weiwei
identified me as a political prisoner
and then did my portrait out of Legos
for the Smithsonian Institution and then
finally amnesty said well okay I guess
he was a political prisoner after all
mm-hmm yeah it was disgusting well
very much think that it's time for us to
move past any expectation or dependency
on the institutional powers and to
become the force to be reckoned with
ourselves and it's very much what we're
trying to do and we've only been able to
do it because very principled brave
people like yourself stood up
immediately when Julian was a cow on his
effectively put in solitary when he's
cut off from communication with everyone
you were among the first 15 people that
within hours of that happening came and
jumped on the script on the stream and
were publicly advocating for him so
thank you for being one of the real
people that doesn't you don't wait for a
paycheck or public credit or anything
you are there out of solidarity and full
props to you for that John it's not
worthy of thanks it's the least I could
do well I certainly am very grateful to
you for that because we could not have
built anything that we have without all
those amazing people behind the scenes
and yourself and the other guests in
front of the scenes who've been pulling
together for Julian and I have been told
that this the existence of this movement
and the groundswell of support that's
coming his way is giving him some
strength and the horrific circumstances
that he finds himself in snow Christie
do you have any last message for the
viewers or for Julian keep up the fight
you know it's easy to to feel powerless
when you consider yourself to be just
one individual but you're not just one
individual this is a movement and there
are people all around the world that are
with us and so we have to keep this
fight up and not relent it's only just
begun this is going to take a long time
well we are doing our best and we're
certainly starting to see some results
in a short timeframe which I'm very
impressed at because I do understand
that someone's fun okay thank you so
much mr. John Kiriakou absolutely gin
dairy whistle I you honor us Angeline
with your presence
so much for being here very very best of
luck thank you